Education and training can help
you feel more confident and
enable you to achieve
successful catheterization.
You can use this step by step
video as support and follow-up
on any training provided.
Always follow the advice and
instructions provided by a clinician,
which are tailored to your individual
medical and lifestyle needs.
So what is intermittent catheterization?
Intermittent catheterization
helps empty your bladder when
your body can't do it on its own.
It involves emptying your
bladder regularly with a hollow
tube with drainage
holes, a catheter.
The catheter is inserted
in your urethra,
which is the tube between
the bladder and the exit,
allowing the urine to flow
down the catheter and out.
Let's briefly go through the
body parts involved in the
urinary system.
Kidney.
Your kidneys are two small bean
shaped organs that clean your
blood and make urine.
Ureter.
The ureters are thin tubes that
carry urine from the kidneys
down to the bladder.
Bladder.
The bladder is a hollow
stretchy organ in your lower
belly that stores urine.
Urethra.
The urethra is the tube that
carries urine from the bladder
out of the body.
And finally, the
urethral opening.
It is quite usual to feel a
little anxious or worried when
starting something new
for the first time,
but with practice and support,
you will soon become more
confident with intermittent
catheterization and it will
soon become a natural part of
your daily routine.
Now, let's talk through how to
use LoFric Elle step by step.
Start by washing your hands
thoroughly with soap and water.
You can also use cleansing
wipes if you don't have access
to running water.
Cleanse your hands again
after catheterization.
Open the upper lid.
Hold the catheter in one hand and
gently bend the upper part to open.
Pull the catheter out.
Connect the container to the
catheter with a gentle twist,
making sure the arrow on
the container points down.
LoFric Elle is an intermittent
catheter with a unique L-shaped
handle that helps you
confidently locate the urethra.
Sitting on the toilet
is ideal for doing IC,
but if not possible,
your clinician will help you find
a position that suits you best.
Tilt your pelvis upwards
and spread your labia.
Hold the handle with
your dominant hand.
Gently and slowly guide the
catheter into the urethra.
The urethral entrance is small
and sometimes hard to see and
using a mirror can help.
It is just above the vaginal
opening and below the clitoris.
It is close to the anus,
so keeping clean is important
to prevent infection.
Once urine starts to flow, the
catheter is in the right place.
Gently insert a little further to
ensure it's fully in your bladder.
When urine stops, slowly
withdraw the catheter.
If more urine flows, pause
and wait before continuing so
the bladder is fully empty.
The unique LoFric surface
coating will ensure that the
catheter remains
smoothly lubricated.
Put the catheter back
inside the container.
Remember, LoFric Elle is a
urinary catheter designed to be
used one time only.
Dispose or carry it in
your bag until disposal.
Please note, the lower
container is recyclable.
How often you catheterize
will vary individually and
also depend upon fluid intake.
Your clinician will advise you
on the right regime for you.
LoFric Elle is your versatile
single use intermittent
catheter ready for you,
whatever your lifestyle needs.